<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Copye of a letter contayning certayne newes, &amp; the articles or requestes of the Deuonshyre &amp; Cornyshe rebelles</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1549</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04967</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15109.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23097459</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23097459</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26224</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04967)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26224)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1797:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Copye of a letter contayning certayne newes, &amp; the articles or requestes of the Deuonshyre &amp; Cornyshe rebelles</title>
                  <author>R. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Day and W. Seres],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.XLIX [1549]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to R.L. by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁸.</note>
                  <note>Title within illustrated border.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devon (England) --  History --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Edward VI, 1547-1553.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26224:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <p>¶ A Copye of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contayning cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne newes, &amp; the Articles or reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonſhyre &amp; Cornyſhe rebelles.</p>
                  <p>(⸫) M.D.XLIX.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:26224:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26224:2"/>
            <head>¶ A copye of a letter contayning cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn newes, and the Articles or requeſtes of the Deuonſhyre and Cornyſhe rebelles.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince my laſte let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſet vnto you; of the newes in theſe parties (Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I wyll kepe my fyrſt promes, for enterchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of lettres) I haue chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed of matter worthye aduertiſment &amp; ſome leaſure to aduertyſe theſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, ſo that I could not with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtye, but ſatiſfye your deſyre, to knowe our newes, as I my ſelf am verie deſirouſe of yours. By my former letters you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtode
<pb facs="tcp:26224:3"/>the dyſordre and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoyall, vprores of the Deuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyremen, whyche at the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng ſemyng to me, to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceded but of ſome wyldenes of theyr braynes, or of ſome igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cance lackynge teachynge, I thought wolde ſone haue bynne tamed wyth authoryte, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed wyth inſtruction, as I vnderſtande the lyke ende hath wel happened of al the diſquiet aſſemblyes, in the other partes of the Realme. But the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Deuonſhyre nowe ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes furthe the rotes of treaſon, the buddes of rebellion, and the fructe of fylthye poperye, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng now pretenſes of treaſon, and auowynge hyghe treaſon, leauynge nowe colour of Rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb facs="tcp:26224:3"/>and reiectyng all trewe religion, nowe come to verye madnes, whyche before were but droncke, and cared not, for the name of rebelles, whych be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were angry to be called treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſers, thys crafte hath the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll to encreaſe hys ſwarme. He taughte the Prieſtes and theyr Captaynes to cal the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple together to defende theyr olde fayth, and therin vſed the name and aucthoryte of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges mayeſtye, hauyng no waye ſo ready, to aſſemble them to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whyche vſuallye is the trompet, that good ſubiectes followeth, two good begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, Ye ſee the deuil vſedthe name of God, and of the Kyng,
<pb facs="tcp:26224:4"/>and in dede, dyrectlye agaynſte God and the Kynge. Wel, nowe was it tyme for hym to worke, he ſawe the aſſemblye dayly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. One part was aſſured his owne, the Romyſh prieſtes and the ſturdy vacabundes. Wyth them he neded not vſe craft, but rather taught them howe to vſe it with others. The other parte were ſymple ignoraunt people, eaſelye diſceyued, and quicklye made the partakers of euyll. Thus the deuyl hauyng made hys bandes (parte of hys owne olde ſeruauntes, parte of a new retynewe) beganne to ſend forth hys embaſſages (the ſame beyng certen requeſtes, as he termed them) to remedye the grieffes of the Deuonſhirmen, to the which the Kynges maieſty, made a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye
<pb facs="tcp:26224:4"/>princely and reaſonable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. Of the whych I receyued ſyxe Copies in printe from you, by M. Mohan, at his laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Court to my Lord pryuey ſeale. And for the ſame I thanke you, prayng you, yf any ſuche lyke thynges come fourth in printe, I may haue ſome ſent me wyth the fyrſt, &amp; yf you wyll ſpeake to the Kynges Prynter in my name, I dare ſay, he wyll not denye you. But nowe to my matter. By theſe embaſſages of his he thought to haue encreaſed hys power, thynkyng in dede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all they (whyche gathered them ſelues together in other partes of the Realme, for pluekynge downe encloſures, &amp; enlargyng of comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) would haue entered in to hys ſeruice and taken hys
<pb facs="tcp:26224:5"/>quarell: but after hys articles were confounded by the kynge, and certen knoweledge came in to Deuonſhyre, by theyr cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours abroad, that the Kentyſh Eſſex, Suffolke, and ſpeciallye Hampſhire, hauing byene with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the iuriſdiccyon of the ſtoute Prelate of Wyncheſter, vtterly dyffyed and abhorred the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonſhyreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, proteſtyng euen in theyr moſte diſorder, that they wolde ſpende theyr lyues agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt all ſuche rancke rebelles tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours &amp; papiſtes. It was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to ſe the newe deuyſes and inuencyons of the pryeſtes and vagabunde Captaynes, for the furtheraunce of theyr firſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. Then bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne they to per ſwade theyr people, that they had all gone to farre to ſhrinke,
<pb facs="tcp:26224:5"/>and that nothinge now ſhoulde helpe them, but ſtoutnes &amp; cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, eyther wolde they now be Lordes, or els haue nothynge, eyther rule, or els not lyue, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make a Kynge, or haue no Kynge, no meane thynge might content them. Theyr fyrſt botye (they thought) ſhoulde be the cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye of Excetter, the next, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpoyle of theyr owne countreye, and ſo conſequently all other partes of the Realme, for Excetter they gape, but they catche nothynge ſauing gonne ſhot, wherof God geues them ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tye. Theyr owne countrey they haue ſo ſpoyled, &amp; ſo diſordered, that it is myſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to heare. The ſonne robbeth the father, the doughter is raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed before the mother, he hathe nothing at night, that had moſt
<pb facs="tcp:26224:6"/>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morninge, &amp; he hath moſte, whiche ought to haue nothing. And how longe he ſhal haue it, there is noo warrant. Two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men go to wrack amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Good true ſubiectes, &amp; wel thie. And other two, be daile pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moted, traitours, and vile vaga boundes. The viler ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of more aucthorite, the honeſter of more ſcruitude. Byeng and ſelling ſea ſeth amonges them, in place whereof is come Robbynge, and reauynge, If hell be in earth, it is amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges them. And the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes there, be the deuils. And the traytours be the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tours, &amp; the reſte of the people forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their King, be as it were ſoules tormented. Alas howe ſhall I be wayle them? ſhall I pray to God that they may pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe?
<pb facs="tcp:26224:6"/>or that they may amend? The one they haue deſerued, the other me thinkes I dare not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of god. For ſettig a ſyde their robberies, their murders, theyr raueſhynges, their ſpoyle of the countrey, and the loſſe of it for many yeres, howe haue they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended their Kyng &amp; ſoueraigne Lorde? How haue they diſpyſed hys name and aucthorite. And (as much as lyeth in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed his credit and renoume. Shal I ſay merely? Euery ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges them, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him ſelf of his good lyuing. And euery euil ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I thinke) is ſory: he was no more wretched, &amp; yet no euilnes nor wretchednes, alloweth any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (yf he wyl not be a ranck traytour) onelye that profeſſion maketh rulers. And becauſe they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge
<pb facs="tcp:26224:7"/>men be comenly brought vp in ſuch ciuylite that hardely they be made traytours, Yt is a common Prouerbe, that truſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge man, truſt gentyll man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> now no place is left but for tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, all other ſciences goeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beggynge with them, and yet I doubt not, but theyr facultye wyll haue the price of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket whiche is a halter and a tre. Thus farre after my accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med maner I haue entreated ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerallytees, and yet ſuch as my harte is ful of, and where my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght I better diſcharge my ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe then wyth one, which wyll take parte thereof, I coulde not tell? But you wyl ſay, ye can la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente the thynges as much as I, but for the matter of my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you wolde deſyre ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb facs="tcp:26224:7"/>newes, or at the leaſte my Iudgement, what I thoughte wolde folowe. For newes, as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>omyſed you in my former let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſende you theyr Articles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I do nowe here include them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he whiche I coulde not well performe before, becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aunged them ſo often, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yſed ſo many, ſomtyme hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome reaſonable, an other tyme. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot one tollerable, ſuche diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tees of heades there was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges them, that for euerye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynde of brayne there was one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aner of Article, the prieſtes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey harped all vpon a playne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nge of Rome, certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> traytours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oulde halow home Cardinall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le, a nombre of vagabon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es wolde haue no Iuſtice, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nde of theues, wolde haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> State of anye Gentlemen
<pb facs="tcp:26224:8"/>and yet to put al in one bagge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſorte of traytours wolde haue nother king nor good ſubiectes. And ſo euery varlet (abounded in hys owne ſenſe) At the laſte, they concluded vpon theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and ſet to their names as ye ſhal ſee in the copie therof. As for other newes (vntil my Lord Priuey ſeale ſhal haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power come to hym, which he daily lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for) I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not haue to write. For my Lord lieth wyth the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges power, here at a place called Honnyton. Who (I aſſure you) hath ſo gouerned theſe parties here, by hys contynuall labour, and wiſdome, that hyther to, the ennemyes dare not come forth out of their dennes (for ſo wold ye cal them) yf ye ſaw the lanes, the hilles, the woodes &amp; ſtraight
<pb facs="tcp:26224:8"/>paſſages, betwyxt vs and them, They lye ſtil nere Exceter as I wrote in my laſt Letters. And not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandynge, the twyſe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hyng of the gates, yet hyther to can they not preuayll. A greate part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth with their fyrſt Captain called vndethyl, a taylour of Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pforde courtney. I thinke they kepe hym ſtyl, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can not fynde hys match, a Captaine wel choſen by the deuil at the firſt. This is for the newes. For my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I dare be bolde wyth you and yet therin I wyll vſe few woordes, becauſe yf I erre, I wil not erre to long a time, I aſſure you, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng more encouraged them, then that they loked all other people being ſturred vp in other parties for encloſures and ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:26224:9"/>lyke grieffe wolde haue taken theyr quarell in hande, ſo nowe nothynge hath ſo muche decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theyr courage as that they heare and knowe the contrarye. Theyr boldenes beyng nowe of theyr owne ſtoore, without hope of partakynge, more deſperate then myghtye and leſſe for theyr purpoſe, then for theyr nombre, very many beynge there aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with them, by force againſt theyr wyll, and manye dayle by repentaunce, reacknoweledgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge theyr dutyes and Subieccyon. And in dede, the very ordre and maner of quyetynge of all other countreys putteth them clerelye from hope to ſtyrre agayne, for they be not ignoraunt that the more parte of the requeſtes of them were ſuch, as bycauſe they
<pb facs="tcp:26224:9"/>could not reaſonable be reiected, being for reformacion of diuers abuſes in the comu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e wealth (not for the bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging in of the Romiſh aucthoryte agaynſt the Kyng, &amp; hys Royall Croune) they be for the moſt parte graunted, in ſuch ſorte as the people haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mercye, and be departed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me wyth good contentacyon, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke good Subiectes. The Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Maieſtye ſuſtayned no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoure, hauyng ruled, his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, bothe wyth Iuſtyce &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, proporcyonallye, and finally the thynges whiche were euyll vſed in the comon wealthe, very lyke to be reformed, part, preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Commiſſion, parte, by Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liament, to the comen profyte of the whole Realme, of ſo good an ende oure rebelles here haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:26224:10"/>moſte ſorye wiſſhing that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people had leaped fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hedge breakinge, to houſe robbing, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dere huntyng, to horſe hunting, from wantonnes, to ſtarke mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as they haue here fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> robbe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries to rape, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rape to murder, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> murder to treaſon &amp; popery, &amp; ſo to the deuil, whereas I fear they wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue. And in dede yf I maye preſume (as I dare do much w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you my freind) to alow the Couſels dede, me thinketh, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> matters haue byne very wel or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered (as it is reported here amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges vs) for although by Iuſtice euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſerueth death, which ryſeth againſte his prince, yea though he haue moche griefe, &amp; that the kinges Maieſty might of Iuſtice make ſlaughter of his people, yet yf there be any place
<pb facs="tcp:26224:10"/>for mercy, it was in this caſe for the Kinge to ſhewe it, vpon hys owne people, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people forget full, not obſtynate, traytours by conſtruccyon of Law, not by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of harte, where the fault of the mooſte parte of them was in dede vnlawfull Aſſemblyes, but wythoute open robberyes, inurder or ſpoyles, referrynge theyr grieffes as Sutours, not Orderars, cryeng for mercye as offendours; not Challengers. And on the other ſyde, the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhewed, was ryght ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, beyng exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, vpon ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther lacked cauſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lacked grace to ſeke for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s mercy, and to ſay my mynde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s one nether of Court nor Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, yf the Kynges ſworde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ghte ſhorte vpon anye, it was
<pb facs="tcp:26224:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26224:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26224:12"/>vpon two kinde of people, ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke Popiſh prieſtes, repynynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the kynges holſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, or vpon the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon runne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, ſeedme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſedicion, of the which we haue plentye here, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte whome. If the martiall law were executed, and were cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rante quoyne in euery ſhyre, as I here ſay, there is a Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the ſame (which I haue not yet ſene, but by youre nexte letters truſt to receiue) I thinke there wolde be as fewe runners abrode, as now there be many. You muſt geue me leaue to talk a litle more after my wounted maner, which is to ſai my mynd fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kly vnto you without offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Nowe me thinketh the ende is ſuch of your matters there, as euery ſtate of people wilbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb facs="tcp:26224:12"/>therwith, and ſo the mooſte trouble wil reſt with theſe tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. For with you, the kinges people which deſerued death, be by mercy preſerued, &amp; the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges euell vſed (as in dede diſcea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes there be in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth) ſhalbe now wel ordered by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And if the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people ſhalbe eaſed of their griefes, the gentelmen ſhall alſo be relieued of them, for ſe how much the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour crieth oute of hys rent, ſo may the gentelman wel crye out of the market, the one as muche greued as the other, &amp; one reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye I truſt ſhal ſerue both. For me thinketh it is no more diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for me, to haue. xx. pound, ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng. xx. pound, then to haue xx. marke, ſpendinge. xx. marke, ſo that my eſtate be kept like w<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26224:13"/>both, you wyll thynke I wryte now at my wyl, becauſe yf ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meber the laſt y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re in the parke at Wynſour when the Court was there, thys queſtion made great argument betwyxre you and me, whether for the amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thinges in the common wealth the fermour ſhould fyrſt abate hys pryce, and then the Landed man his rent, or in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary order, at whyche tyme, I remembre you ſtode vpon one poynte, whych I could not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, that the Gentylman by deere byeng, was dryu on to let deere, and I vpon an other poynte (not al vntrewe) that the deere hyrynge made deere fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, But where the fault fyrſt beganne, neyther of vs woulde graunt to the other, neuer the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:26224:13"/>ſo wayghty a matter it is, as no wayes to be diſeuſſed but by Parliament. Where when the argument is at an ende, it may be citablyſhed by a lawe, wherof there was neuer more wkelyhood, becauſe the ameu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement therof, wyl helpe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as well Lordes and Gentil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, as al other Commoners, no man hauyng eauſe to repyne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt it, but ſuche as gather, not to ſpende and improue their lyuinges not For their charges, as many Geutilmen haue done, but for their coffers, So that to conclude, improuemet alone ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth no man ryche, but improue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and ſparynge. But what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edle I wyth thys matter and yet what dare I net to you my fryende, by Sayncte G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orge
<pb facs="tcp:26224:14"/>I ſaye to you merely out of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urde, no one thinge maketh me more angry with theſe rebelles then one article, which toucheth me on the quicke, and I beleue, there be few in the realme, but it will make them ſmart, to forgoe his Abbey &amp; Chauntrye landes wherin I for my part am ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that if I ſhould fight wyth thoſe traitours, I wold for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry two ſtrokes to be ſtricken for treaſon ſtrike on to kepe my la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, the which I bought to ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, to deliuer it at a papiſtes ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poyntement. Thus I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded in woordes, &amp; yet you ſhal counte it littel, becauſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is large, &amp; therby you muſte meaſure me, &amp; not by my lynes, One thing I wil ye ſhal marke and then I ende, the matter of
<pb facs="tcp:26224:14"/>Cardynal Pole (as in this caſe) of greate importaunce, lyke as I am ſure my Lord Protectour is aduertiſed, for emonges theſe rebelles, the chiefe Captayne of all, ſauinge one, was the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of Excetters man, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth the matter of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall ſo much, as in dede, he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth no other matter. Hys name is Berry, one of them which ſub ſcrybed the Articles. Yf ye can conuenientlye ſende me a Dagg when the Kynges Maieſtyes ordynance commeth doune. Ye ſhall receyue moneye for the ſame of my Brother Henry. Ye ſhall take payne to do my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble commendacyons to myne olde Mayſter (good Syr Anthonye Dennye knyght) and eſpecyally to my Cooſyn May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb facs="tcp:26224:15"/>John Peres of the Garde, who I woulde were here with one or two hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oreth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Garde, to knecke theſe knaues wyth theyr Halo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s. Thus f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re ye mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elye wel, and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> you, as I do, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> maye mete merclye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:26224:15"/>
            <head>The Articles of vs the Commoners of Deuonſhyre and Lornewall in diuers Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes vp Eaſt and Weſt of Excertor.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſt we wyll haue all the general counſell &amp; holy decrees of our for fathers obſerued, kept and performed, and who ſo euer ſhal agayne ſaye them, we holde them as Heretikes.</p>
            <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we will haue the Lawes of our Souerayne Lord kyng Henry the. vin, concernynge the ſyxe articles, to be in vſe again, as in hys tyme they were.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we will haue the make in Latten, as was before, &amp; cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated by the Pryeſt wythoute any man or woman co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng wyth hym.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26224:16"/>¶ Item we wyll haue the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament hange ouer the hyeghe aulter, and there to be worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as it was wount to be, and they whiche will not therto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, we wyl haue them dye lyke heretykes agaynſt the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyque fayth.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we wyll haue the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulter but at Eaſter delyuered to the lay people, and then but in one kynde.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we wil that our Curat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhal miniſter the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Baptiſine at all tymes aſwel in the weke daye as on the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daye.</p>
            <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we wyl haue holy bread and holy water made euery ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye, Palmes and aſſhes at the tymes accuſtomed, Images to be ſet vp again in euery church,
<pb facs="tcp:26224:16"/>and all other auncient olde Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonyes vſed heretofore, by our mother the holy Church.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we wil not receyue the newe ſeruyce becauſe it is but lyke a Chriſtmas ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, but we wyll haue oure olde ſeruice of Mattens, maſſe, Euenſong and proceſſion in Latten as it was before. And ſo we the Cornyſhe men (wherof certen of vs vnder ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deno Englyſh) vtterly refuſe thys newe Englyſh.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we wyll haue euerye preacher in his ſermon, &amp; euery Pryeſt at hys maſſe, praye ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by name for the ſoules in purgatory, as oure forefathers dyd.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we wyll haue the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and al bokes of ſcripture in Englyſh to be called in agayn,
<pb facs="tcp:26224:17"/>for we be enformed that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Clergye, ſhal not of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time confound the heretykes.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we wyll haue Doctor Moreman and Doctor Criſpin which holde our opinions to be ſauely ſent vnto vs and to them we requyre the Kinges maieſty, to geue ſome certain liuinges, to preache amenges vs our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholycke fayth.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we thinke it very mete becauſe the lord Cardinal Pole is of the kynges bloode, ſhould not only haue hys pardon, but alſo ſent for to Rome, &amp; promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be of the kinges cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we wyll that no Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylman ſhall haue any more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes then one to wayte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym excepte he maye diſpende one hundreth marke land and
<pb facs="tcp:26224:17"/>for euerye hundreth marke we thynke it reaſonable he ſhould haue a man.</p>
            <p>¶ Item we wyll that the halfe parte of the Abbey landes and Chauntrye landes, in euerye mans poſſeſſyons, how ſo euer he cam by them, be geuen again to two places, where two of the chief Abbeis was with in euery Countye, where ſuche half part ſhalbe taken out, and there to be eſtablyſhed a place for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout perſons, whych ſhall pray for the Kyng and the common wealth, and to the ſame we wyll haue al the almes of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che boxe geuen for theſe ſeuen yeres.</p>
            <p>¶ Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the particular grief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes of our Countreye. We wyll haue them ſo ordered, as Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey
<pb facs="tcp:26224:18"/>Arundell, &amp; Henry Braye the Kynges Maior of Bodma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhall enforme the Kynges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye, yf they maye haue ſalue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duet vnder the Kynges great Seale, to paſſe and repaſſe, with an Heroalde at Armes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>¶ By vs
<list>
                     <item>Humfrey Arundell.</item>
                     <item>Berry Thomas Vnderhyll.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Sloeman.</item>
                     <item>Wyllyam Segar.</item>
                     <item>Chiefe Capytaynes.</item>
                     <item>Iohn Tompſon Pryeſte.</item>
                     <item>Henry Bray Maior of Bodma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </item>
                     <item>Henry Lee Maior of Tortiton</item>
                     <item>Roger Barret Prieſte.</item>
                     <item>The foure Gouernours of the Campes.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
